Early visions of wireless power
نسخة سابقة من الطاقة اللاسلكية
actually were thought of by Nikola Tesla
حقيقتاً فكر بها نيكول تيسلا
basically about 100 years ago.
ببساطة قبل حوالي مائة سنة
The thought that
الفكرة هي
you wouldn't want to transfer electric power wirelessly,
انك لا تريد أن تنقل طاقة كهربائية لاسلكياً في الجو
no one ever thought of that.
لا أحد فكر بهذا مطلقاً
They thought, "Who would use it if you didn't?"
فقط فكروا " بأنه من سيستخدمها إن لم تفعل أنت
And so, in fact, he actually set about
إذا وبالتالي ، فقد جلس حول
doing a variety of things.
فعل العديد من الأشياء
Built the Tesla coil. This tower was built
بناء كويل تيسلا ، هذا البرج تم بنائه
on Long Island back at the beginning of the 1900s.
في لونق أيلاند سابقاً في بداية القرن التاسع عشر
And the idea was, it was supposed to be able to transfer power
والفكرة كانت ، أنه كان المفترض أن نقدر على نقل الطاقة
anywhere on Earth.
إلى أي في مكان في الأرض
We'll never know if this stuff worked. Actually, I think the
ونحن لن نعرف ما إذا عملت هذه الأشياء ، في الواقع أعتقد
Federal Bureau of Investigation
أن المجلس الفيدرالي للتحقيق
took it down for security purposes,
أغلق المشروع لأسباب أمنية
sometime in the early 1900s.
في وقت سابق بداية ال 1900
But the one thing that did come out of electricity
ولكن الشي الوحيد الذي خرج من الكهرباء
is that we love this stuff so much.
أننا نحب هذه الأشياء كثيراً
I mean, think about how much we love this.
أقصد فكروا جيداً كم نحب هذا
If you just walk outside, there are trillions of dollars
إذا مشيتم خارجاً سترون تريلونات الدولارات
that have been invested in infrastructure around the world,
التي تم أستثمارها في البنية التحتية حول العالم
putting up wires to get power from where it's created
لوضع أسلاك لأخذ الطاقة من حيث تنتج
to where it's used.
إلى حيث ستستخدم
The other thing is, we love batteries.
والشي الأخر هو ، أننا نحب البطاريات
And for those of us that have an environmental element to us,
وأولئك منا الذين لديهم حس بيئي
there is something like 40 billion
هنالك تقريباً 40 مليون
disposable batteries built every year
بطارية تصنع كل سنة
for power that, generally speaking,
لطاقة عاده كما نقول
is used within a few inches or a few feet
تستخدم لبوصات صغيرة أو حتى أقدام
of where there is very inexpensive power.
لذا تعتبر طاقة غالية الثمن
So, before I got here,
لذا قبل أن أصل إلى هنا
I thought, "You know, I am from North America.
فكرت " تعرفون أنني من أمريكا الشمالية
We do have a little bit of a reputation in the United States."
نحن لدينا تقريباً سمعة في الولايات المتحدة"
So I thought I'd better look it up first.
لذا فكرت أن أبحثها قليلاً
So definition number six is the North American
أذاً التعريف الأمريكي الشمالي السادس
definition of the word "suck."
تعريف لكلمة مقرف
Wires suck, they really do.
الأسلاك مقرفة، أنها فعلاً كذلك
Think about it. Whether that's you in that picture
فكروا فيها ، ما إذا كنت أنت في تلك الصورة
or something under your desk.
أو شي تحت مكتبك
The other thing is, batteries suck too.
الشي الأخر هو أن البطاريات سيئة كذلك
And they really, really do.
وهي فعلا فعلا كذلك
Do you ever wonder what happens to this stuff?
هل فكرتم بكيف ينتهي بهذه الأشياء .؟
40 billion of these things built.
40 مليون بطارية تصنع سنوياً
This is what happens.
هذا ما يحدث لها
They fall apart, they disintegrate,
أنها تنهار وتفرغ
and they end up here.
وينتهي بها المطاف هنا
So when you talk about expensive power,
لذا عندما نتحدث عن الطاقة الغالية
the cost per kilowatt-hour
تكلفة الكيلو وات في الساعة
to supply battery power to something
لتوفير طاقة بطارية لتشغيل شي ما
is on the order of two to three hundred pounds.
في الأغلب 200 أو 300 جنية
Think about that.
فكروا في ذلك
The most expensive grid power in the world
أغلى سبيل طاقة في العالم
is thousandths of that.
هو ألوف من ذلك
So fortunately, one of the other definitions
لذا باالتالي ، واحد من التعريفات
of "suck" that was in there, it does create a vacuum.
لكلمة سئ هنا ، أنها تنتج حالة تفريغ
And nature really does abhor a vacuum.
والطبيعة فعلا ترفض هذا التفريغ
What happened back a few years ago
ما حدث مؤخرا قبل كم سنة
was a group of theoretical physicists at MIT
كان مجموعه من الباحثين الفيزيائين في MIT
actually came up with this concept of transferring power over distance.
هم فعلاً أتو بهذا المفهوم لتحويل الطاقة عبر المسافات
Basically they were able to light a 60 watt light bulb
بداية تمكنوا من أضاءة لمبة 60 وات
at a distance of about two meters.
من على بعد مترين
It got about 50 percent of the efficiency --
وتقدمو ، فوصلت إلى 50% من فعاليتها
by the way, that's still a couple thousand times
وبالمناسبة هذا فقط الاف المرات
more efficient than a battery would be, to do the same thing.
أكثر فعالية من البطاريات لتفعل نفس الشي
But were able to light that,
ولكنهم هل تمكنوا من أشعال هذا
and do it very successfully.
وقد نجحوا فعلاً
This was actually the experiment. So you can see
هذه كانت التجربة ، حيث ترون هنا
the coils were somewhat larger.
لفة الأسلاك كانت أكبر
The light bulb was a fairly simple task, from their standpoint.
إضاءة اللمبة كانت تجربة سهلة ، من وجهه نظرهم
This all came from a professor
هذا كله آتى من بروفسور
waking up at night to the third night in a row
أستيقظ في ليلة لـ3 ليلال متواصلة
that his wife's cellphone was beeping
لأن جوال زوجته يطنطن
because it was running out of battery power.
لأن بطاريته فرغت
And he was thinking, "With all the electricity that's out there in the walls,
وفكر حينها " مع كل تلك الكهرباء في تلك الجدران
why couldn't some of that just come into the phone so I could get some sleep?"
لم نستطع توصيلها فقط للجوال حتى أتمكن من النوم قليلاً "
And he actually came up with this concept
وهو فعلاً جاء بهذا المفهوم
of resonant energy transfer.
لإعادة تعريف نقل الطاقة
But inside a standard transformer are two coils of wire.
ولكن في داخل كل ناقل عادي هناك لفتين من الأسلاك
And those two coils of wire are really, really close to each other,
وهذان السلكان هما فعلاً قريبتان من بعضهما
and actually do transfer power
حينما ينقلون الطاقة
magnetically and wirelessly, only over a very short distance.
مغناطيسياً أو لاسلكياً ، فقط على بعد مسافة قريبة
What Dr. Soljacic figured out how to do
ما أكتشفه د. قيلبرت هو كيفيه عملها
was separate the coils in a transformer
فقد فصلنا السلكين في المحول
to a greater distance than the size of those transformers
لمسافة أبعد من حجم هذه المحولات
using this technology, which is not dissimilar
بإستخدام هذه التقنية ، والتي لا تختلف كثيراً
from the way an opera singer shatters a glass on the other side of the room.
بطريقة مغني الأوبرا حينما يكسر الزجاج في الجانب الأخر من الغرفة
It's a resonant phenomenon
وهي فعلاً ظاهرة مؤثرة
for which he actually received a MacArthur Fellowship Award,
والتي حصل على جائزة مكارثر للباحثين
which is nicknamed the Genius Award,
والتي أسمها الشائع جائزة العباقرة
last September, for his discovery.
في سبتمبر الماضي، لإكتشافه المذهل هذا
So how does it work?
إذاً كيف تعمل .؟
Imagine a coil. For those of you that are engineers,
تخيلو لفة أسلاك ، خصوصاً لهؤلاء منكم المهندسين
there's a capacitor attached to it too.
مشبوكة بمكثف كهربائي كذلك
And if you can cause that coil to resonate,
وإذا تمكنت من جعلها تدور
what will happen is it will pulse
ماذا سيحدث هل ستعمل
at alternating current frequencies --
على موجه بديلة
at a fairly high frequency, by the way.
على موجه عالية نسبياً ، وعلى سبيل المثال
And if you can bring another device
وإذا تمكنت من إحضار أداة أخرى
close enough to the source,
قريبة كفاية من المصدر
that will only work at exactly that frequency,
والذي سيعمل على نفس تلك الموجة
you can actually get them to do what's called strongly couple,
انتم تستطيعون فعلاً ان تخلقو منها الزوج القوي
and transfer magnetic energy between them.
وتحولون الطاقة المغناطيسية بينهما
And then what you do is, you start out with electricity,
ثم ما تفعلونه هو ، انكم تبدأون بالكهرباء
turn it into magnetic field, take that magnetic field,
تحولونها إلى طاقة مغناطيسية ، وتأخذون هذا المجال المغناطيسي
turn it back into electricity,
وتحولونه مرة أخرى إلى كهرباء
and then you can use it.
لتتمكنو من إستخدامه
Number one question I get asked.
السؤال رقم 1 الذي يطرح عليّ دائما ً
I mean, people are worried about cellphones being safe.
ما أقصده هو خوف الناس من كون الهاتف المحمول آمناً
You know. What about safety?
كما تعرفون ، ماذا عن السلامة ؟
The first thing is this is not a "radiative" technology.
أولاً هذه ليست تقنية إشعاعية
It doesn't radiate.
فهي لا تشع
There aren't electric fields here. It's a magnetic field.
فليس هناك مجال كهربائي ، بل هو مجال مغناطيسي
It stays within either what we call the source,
فهي تبقى بالداخل ، بما نسميه المصدر
or within the device.
أو في داخل الآداة
And actually, the magnetic fields we're using
في الحقيقة المجال المغناطيسي الذي نستعمله هنا
are basically about the same as the Earth's magnetic field.
هو بالأساس مشابه كثيراًُ للمجال المغناطيسي للأرض
We live in a magnetic field.
فنحن نعيش على مجال مغناطيسي
And the other thing that's pretty cool about the technology is
والشي الأخرى العجيب في هذه التقنية
that it only transfers energy to things that work at exactly the same frequency.
أنها تنقل الطاقة إلى الأشياء التي تعمل على نفس الموجة بالتحديد
And it's virtually impossible in nature to make that happen.
ونظرياً هذا مستحيل في الطبيعة أن نستطيع فعل ذلك
Then finally we have governmental bodies everywhere
وفي الأخر سنجد الجهات الحكومية في كل مكان
that will regulate everything we do.
والتي ستضع التشاريع لكل ما نعمله
They've pretty much set field exposure limits,
وقد فعلو الكثير لوضع المحددات للتعرض للمجالات المغناطيسية
which all of the things in the stuff I'll show you today
وكل تلك الأشياء الذي سأريكم إياها اليوم
sort of sit underneath those guidelines.
تقريباُ تتبع كل تلك المحددات
Mobile electronics.
الإلكترونيات المحمولة
Home electronics.
الإلكترونيات المنزلية
Those cords under your desk, I bet everybody here
كل تلك الأسلاك تحت مكتبك ، أرهن بأن كلكم هنا
has something that looks like that or those batteries.
لديه شي مشابه لهذا ، أو لتلك البطاريات
There are industrial applications.
هنالك تطبيقات صناعية
And then finally, electric vehicles.
ثم أخيراُ ، السيارات الكهربائية
These electric cars are beautiful.
تلك السيارات الكهربائية جميلة
But who is going to want to plug them in?
ولكن من يريد أن يشبكهم دائما بالفيش ؟
Imagine driving into your garage -- we've built a system to do this --
تخيل القيادة إلى مرآبك ، "فقد بنينا نظاماً كهذا "
you drive into your garage, and the car charges itself,
حيث تقود إلى المرآب ، وحينها تشحن السيارة نفسها
because there is a mat on the floor that's plugged into the wall.
لأن هنالك فرشة في الأرض ، والمشبوكة بالجدار
And it actually causes your car to charge safely and efficiently.
والتي حقيقتاً تجعل سيارتك تشحن بأمان وفعالية
Then there's all kinds of other applications. Implanted medical devices,
وهنالك العديد من التطبيقات ، المعدات الطبية المزروعة بالداخل
where people don't have to die of infections anymore
فنحن يا عالم لانحتاج إن نموت من الإلتهاب بعد الأن
if you can seal the thing up.
إذا تنمكنت من إحكام إغلاقها
Credit cards, robot vacuum cleaners.
بطاقات الإئتمان ، روبوتات الكنس للتنظيف
So what I'd like to do is take a couple minutes
وماأريد أن أفعله هو أن أخذ دقيقتين
and show you, actually, how it works.
لأريكم ، كيف تعمل في الواقع
And what I'm going to do is to show you pretty much what's here.
وما سأفعله هو أن أريكم ماذا لدينا هنا
You've got a coil.
لديك كويل
That coil is connected to an R.F. amplifier
السلك مشبوك بمقوي الموجات الكهرومغناطيسية
that creates a high-frequency oscillating magnetic field.
والتي تنشي موجه عالية موفرةً مجال مغناطيسياً
We put one on the back of the television set.
نضع واحدة خلف قاعدة التلفزيون
By the way, I do make it look a little bit easier than it is.
وبالمناسبة فإنني أحاول تبسيطها عما هي عليه
There's lots of electronics and secret sauce
هنالك الكثير من الإلكترونيات والخلطة السرية
and all kinds of intellectual property that go into it.
وكل أنواع حقوق الملكية الفكرية التي تتبعها
But then what's going to happen is, it will create a field.
ولكن الذي سيحدث هو أنها ستخلق مجالاً
It will cause one to get created
حيث ستسبب أن ينشئ مجال
on the other side.
أخر في المجانب المقابل
And if the demo gods are willing,
وإذا أشتغلت التجربة بمشيئة الله
in about 10 seconds or so we should see it.
في خلال 10 ثوان يجب أن نراها
The 10 seconds actually are because we --
حيث أن ال10ثوان في الحقيقة بسبب أننا
I don't know if any of you have ever thought about plugging a T.V. in
لا أعرف مإذا كان أحد منكم فكر توصيل التلفزيون
when you use just a cord.
بإستخدام سلك فقط
Generally, you have to go over and hit the button. So I thought
غالباً يجب أن تقوم وتضغط الزر
we put a little computer in it that has to wake up
فقط وضعنا بها كمبيوتر صغير والذي يجعلها تصحو
to tell it to do that.
الذي يجب أن يفيق ليأمرها أن تفعل ذلك
So, I'll plug that in.
أذاً ، سأشبك هذا
It creates a magnetic field here.
حيث ستنشئ مجالاً مغناطيسياً
It causes one to be created out here.
الذي سيسبب نشوء أخر هنا كذلك
And as I said, in sort of about 10 seconds
و كما قلت في خلال 10 ثواني
we should start to see ...
يجب أن نبدأ برؤية
This is a commercially --
حيث أن هذا في السوق
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
available color television set.
تلفزيون ملون عادي مما هو موجود في الأسواق
Imagine, you get one of these things. You want to hang them on the wall.
تخيل حصولك على إحدى تلك الأشياء لتعلقها في جدارك
How many people want to hang them on the wall?
كم عدد الأشخاص الذين يرغبون بتعليقها على جدارهم ؟
Think about it. You don't want those ugly cords coming down.
فكرو فيها ، أنتم لاتريدون تلك الأسلاك القبيحة في الأسفل
Imagine if you can get rid of it.
تخيل أنه يمكنك التخلص منها
The other thing I wanted to talk about was safety.
والشي الأخر الذي أو الحديث عنه هو درجة الأمان
So, there is nothing going on. I'm okay.
حيث ليس هنالك شي يحدث ، أنا بخير
And I'll do it again, just for safety's sake.
وسأفعلها مرة أخرى فقط من أجل الأمان
Almost immediately, though, people ask,
وعلى الفور بدأت الناس تسأل
"How small can you make this? Can you make this small enough?"
كم ستستطيع أن تصغرها ؟ هل تستطيع أن تجعلها صغيره كفاية ؟
Because remember Dr. Soljacic's original idea
لأنه تذكر فكرة د.سوجلاك الأصلية
was his wife's cellphone beeping.
كانت بسبب طنين هاتف زوجته
So, I wanted to show you something.
لذا وددت أن أريكم شيئاَ
We're an equal opportunity designer of this sort of thing.
نحن فرصنا متساوية في تصميم مثل هذه الأشياء
This a Google G1.
هذا هاتف قوقل G1
You know, it's the latest thing that's come out.
تعرفون أنه أخر ما نزل للأسواق
It runs the Android operating system.
حيث يعمل على نظام تشغيل أندرويد
I think I heard somebody talk about that before.
أظن أنني سمعت أحداً تكلم عن ذلك مسبقاً
It's odd. It has a battery.
أنه غريب ، حيث به بطارية
It also has coiled electronics
وبه كذلك إلكترونيات موصلة به
that WiTricity has put into the back of it.
والذي وضعتها "كهرباء لا سلكية" على ظهر الهاتف
And if I can get the camera --
وإذا تمكنت من الحصول على الكاميرا،
okay, great --
حسناً ممتاز
you'll see, as I get sort of close...
سترون كلما قربت منه
you're looking at a cellphone powered completely wirelessly.
ستظرون إلى محمول مشحون لاسلكياً بالكامل
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And I know some of you are Apple aficionados.
وأعلم أن من منكم من يهوى أبل
So, you know they don't make it easy at Apple to get inside their phones.
حيث تعلمون أنهم لم يجعلونها سهلة أن تضع شيئاً بداخله
So we put a little sleeve on the back,
لذا وضعنا ملصقاً على ظهره
but we should be able to get this guy to wake up too.
ولكن يجب أن نتمكن من رؤية أخينا يصحو كذلك
And those of you that have an iPhone recognize the green center.
هؤلاء منكم الذين لديهم الـ Iphone يعرفون المركز الأخضر
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And Nokia as well.
ونوكيا كذلك
You'll see that what we did there is put a little thing in the back, to do that,
سترون أن ما فعلناه هو وضع أشياء صغيره خلفها لتفعل ذلك
and it probably beeps, actually, as it goes on as well.
وقد ترن في الحقيقة عندما تعمل كذلك
But they typically use it to light up the screen.
ولكنهم يستخدمونها ببساطة لإضاءة الشاشة
So, imagine these things could go ... they could go in your ceiling.
إذا تخيلو هذه الأشياء على سقوفكم
They could go in the floor. They could go, actually, underneath your desktop.
أو على أرضياتكم ، كذلك تحت مكاتبكم
So that when you walk in or you come in from home,
حيث عندما تدخلون عائدين للبيت
if you carry a purse, it works in your purse.
وتحملون معكم شنطة يدكم ،ستعمل بداخلها
You never have to worry about plugging these things in again.
لن تحتاجو أن تقلقو على شبك هذ الأشياء أبداً
And think of what that would do for you.
وفركوا فيما يمكن أن يخدمكم هذا
So I think in closing,
إذا أفكر في خاتمة لحديثي
sort of in the immortal visions of The New Yorker magazine,
شيئاً من الرؤية الخالدة لمجلة نيويركر
I thought I'd put up one more slide.
ففكرت بوضع شريحة أخرى
And for those of you who can't read it, it says,
ولأولئك الذين لا يستطيعون قرائتها ، أنها تقول
"It does appear to be some kind of wireless technology."
"أنها فعلاً تبدو كتقنية لاسلكية"
So, thank you very much.
وشكراً جزيلاً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)